And so it begins ...

Day 00000: Saturday, 2015 March 07

My story unfortunately begins in data loss. While on the verge of finally acquiring a short domain name, my server's hard drive was hit with a poorly-timed power surge and died. This was one of the few times where my laptop's hard drive was empty. I had just transferred everything from my laptop to my server to install a new OS (Debian 8) on my laptop. I lost everything I had in the digital world, including my website, my research, my source code, my artwork, my private keys, and my KeePassX database. By losing that KeePassX database, I lost access to all my accounts across the entire Internet. I will need to begin anew. Learn from this. One copy of your data is never enough. You need at least two copies minimum at any given time of anything worth keeping.

Most accounts offer you a way to recover the password, but this password recovery option, if it exists, usually involves either a password reminder email (which is proof that your password is insecurely stored in their database), a password reset email, or "security" questions. In the case of the former two, you need access to your email account on file, which means I would have needed to have already recovered my email password. In the case of the latter, I would need to have known the answers to the "security" questions. The problem with "security" questions is that they are not secure at all. Anyone who knows you well enough can answer them and hijack your account. It is therefore recommended that you use these fields as extra passwords, and not actually answer them honestly. That means that these extra passwords would have been in my KeePassX database, and I could not answer them. I still highly recommend not answering these questions truthfully, using long, random-character passwords, and using KeePassX to store them, all in the name of security, but *please* keep backup copies of your most important files, such as your KeePassX database itself.

I began my day today waking up to a letter from the //st. registry saying that my request to register the short name //y.st. had been approved. A link was provided in the letter to make the purchase, as well as instructions that if Payex gave me trouble as it had some other users, to try PayPal. This did not bode well for me. PayPal has been a huge thorn in my side in the past, refusing to take my credit and debit cards without an account, refusing to let me pay from an account at all, refusing to delete my account for several months, demanding copies of my photo ID, my Social Security card, and my credit card statements, demanding that I give PayPal complete and total access to my bank account, et cetera. Even after meeting all of PayPal's demands (with the exception of giving them any access at all to my bank account) and getting support to unlock the account for use and/or deletion, every time I would log in to delete the account, PayPal would re-lock the account on me so I would have to deal with the same demands and PayPal support again. PayPal is not a viable option. If Payex is giving people grief, there is no particular reason why I would not be one of those people, and I know for a fact that PayPal won't work for me.

Surprisingly though, the Payex payment went through with no hassle. I now own //y.st.. And thus begins day zero.

The //st. registry does not seem to hash its user's passwords, which worries me a bit. They are able to send password reminders, which means the passwords are stored in a retrievable form. However, the //st. registry also does not have the idiotic telephone number requirement. My domain name was the one thing that bound me to to the deprecated telephone number system. After years, I am finally free!

Seriously though, I wish people would switch to a better system already. For example, SIP addresses are more memorable, more human-readable, more decentralized, and if you use your own domain, more portable. They are much better than the strings of digits we call "telephone numbers". It's worth noting that people have added some portability to telephone numbers, but it's hacky and less functional than SIP address portability. By default, a telephone number acts similarly to an IP address, pointing out exactly where a call needs to go. However, a ported telephone number instead acts more like a domain name, not pointing itself to the location the call must reach, but instead representing a record that must be looked up to find the address the call must reach. This would be like having IP addresses and domain names be indistinguishable, existing within a single name space! If my understanding is correct, every time you place a call or send a text message using a telephone number, the telephone company must first consult their lookup table to see if your number is ported, and if it is, use the information in the database. Then, if it isn't ported, they just use the telephone number as the basic address it was meant to be. As for being less portable than SIP, if you own the domain name your SIP account is attached to, you could deactivate your account whenever you like, reactivating it later. With ported telephone numbers, you must always be paying a telephone service provider to keep your number from falling into someone else's hands, even if you don't plan to use it for an extended period of time (maybe you are on vacation or something). The system is broken and needs to be replaced, possibly by SIP.

The only record types offered by the //st. registry's default DNS though are A, CNAME, MX, and TXT. While it's awesome that the //st. registry offers DNS as all, I may need to find an alternative DNS provider in the future to enable use of SERV records.

I managed to generate my first self-signed wildcard SSL certificates today, for use with this domain and my onion domain. The user ghetto on #nottor was very helpful in helping me figure out how to get OpenSSL to generate the certificate, as was this page by Richard Levitte and a post on Stack Overflow by jww. It seems OpenSSL is a bit broken, and using the subjectAltName field requires editing the configuration files owned by root every time you want to use different values, which should be each time you generate a certificate.

Apache is configured, OpenSSL is configured ... The next step will be to get an email server configured. Once I am reachable by email, I should be able to begin rebuilding my Internet presence. I've begun configuring Dovecot, but have not gotten the mail server fully set up yet.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

I almost sold my domain name for a drawing of a duck today.

Day 00002: Monday, 2015 March 09

I spent the day doing research attempting to figure out how to get my mail server configured and running properly. I had no luck. Something had been eating at my mind for a while though: ISPs are known to block traffic coming from their customers on the mail port as a lazy way of blocking spam. I decided to check to see if my ISP is one of them. It seems that they are indeed blocking traffic on port 25, both incoming and outgoing. This has had nothing to do with why I can't figure out how to get the mail server configured, as the thing still doesn't even work on the local network, but it does mean that I should give up trying. Even if I get the server figured out, it will all be for nothing. I will instead set up an account with someone else to get email service running on one of their servers.

(For the record, I'm no fan of Comcast. Comcast is a freedom-hating, evil corperation that wants to destroy net neutrality. However, I'm not the one paying the household Internet connection bill, so I don't get a say in our choice of ISPs.)

I decided to choose Zoho to provide my email service for the time being. I'm not enthusiastic about their terms of service, but they are tolerable for now. Setting up email access through them will get me up and running, and if I need to switch providers later, I can do so. It's worth noting though that the registration form and the terms of service seem to maybe be at odds with one another. The terms of service say You agree to: a) provide true, accurate, current and complete information about yourself as prompted by the sign up process;, while the registration form says (in reference to both the first name field and the last name field) This must be between 2 to 30 characters and can contain letters, numbers, underscores, dot(.). If Zoho was asking for a legal first and last name, they would not be allowing underscores or digits. It is also highly likely that they would disallow dots. I can thus only assume that the first and last name are required to be accurate, but not necessarily a person's legal names. I used my legal name anyway due to it being already publicly-available in the whois records. However, the form presented the following error message: We are unable to process your request now. Please try again after sometime or contact support@zohoaccounts.com. I will try again tomorrow. If that does not work, I might try contacting support or I might try finding another email provider, though the latter will be quite difficult unless I can scrape together the funds to set up a paid account.

An explanation for today's weblog entry's title can be found in the log of #Volatile. A summery lies below:

[18:21:06] <Japex> Yst: I'll buy y.st for $1
[18:21:13] <mistedwind> 2$
[18:21:40] <mistedwind> okay
[18:21:53] <mistedwind> how about $5 and a drawing of a duck? final offer.
[18:22:29] <Yst> Japex: I don't know how much it added up to after currency translation and translation fees, but it was more than that. Besides, I spent nearly a month finding an available short name. I'm not giving it up easily.
[18:22:53] <mistedwind> Yst: the duck though
[18:23:33] <Yst> mistedwind: The duck is tempting, but I think I'll have to pass. I've wanted a short name since I before I registered my first name.
[18:25:22] <mistedwind> >Yst's weblog entry 3-9-15 I almost sold my domain name for a drawing of a duck today.
[18:25:47] <Yst> mistedwind: Mind if I post that?
[18:25:52] <Yst> With your name?
[18:25:56] <mistedwind> go ahead
[18:26:02] <Yst> Sweet.
[18:26:06] <Japex> Why would mistedwind mind?
[18:26:22] <mistedwind> Japex: Yst is being polite, you should follow suit.
[18:26:46] <Yst> It's not likely mistedwind would mind, but I do have to ask just in case. I don't want to piss people off without good reason.
[18:28:29] <Yst> Japex: Can I take that as a statement that you won't mind if I repost what you said as well?
[18:28:40] <Japex> Nah, I don't mind.
[18:28:51] <Japex> If I'm saying something in a public channel. I couldn't really care less.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Twitter and pinentry vex me, but email (including PGP) is up

Day 00004: Wednesday, 2015 March 11

I registered an account with Freeola today, thinking I could set up email at my own domain through them. However, it seems they only offer that service for domains registered through them. Even if I wanted to transfer my domain to Freeola, which I don't, Freeola does not support //st. domains.

I have still not received a response from Zoho, but I decided to try again to register there. Registration is back to being functional. So now, I have email up and running.

The main reason I needed to get my email account set up so quickly is that without an email address, you can't register accounts in most places. Now that I have email access, I began setting up accounts. First, I tried to register an account at the Volatile Club. However, services are currently down. Next, I registered at OFTC. After that, I thought a bit, and decided to get onto Twitter. It's a decent source of quick news for when I'm on my break at work. However, Twitter does not seem to like me. They locked up my account within about ten minutes, and I hadn't even done anything. I couldn't tweet to Twitter support with my Twitter account on lockdown, so I decided to try email support, which meant I needed to get my PGP key set up.

And cue more technical difficulties. As you've no doubt guessed from my previous entries, I rely on a password database application called KeePassX. I don't actually know any of my passwords, they are all stored in an encrypted database, and I paste them into whatever application is asking for a given password. Enigmail refuses to allow me to paste the password needed to use my PGP key! I ended up sending the letter without signing it because I thought it would take at least until tomorrow to fix the problem.

I tried to register at SourceForge, because the Enigmail forums are hosted there. No dice. I wanted to report the issue there and find out for sure if it was an accidental bug in need of fixing (similar to the bug in Irrlicht that prevents pasting text into Minetest) or an intentional anti-feature. With nowhere else to turn on the Enigmail issue, I decided to ask around in #nottor and see if anyone there knew of a better email client and/or plugin for sending PGP-encrypted/signed email. Instead of recommending a new mail setup, cacahuatl showed me how to trick Enigmail into accepting the password! Additionally, it seems that the issue is an intentional anti-feature, not a bug. This auto-type feature of KeePassX is great news though! Using this same feature that bypasses Enigmail's anti-feature, I can also work around Irrlicht's bug. I can now store my Minetest passwords in my KeePassX database.

At work today, I learned that both the government and criminals have access to these scary devices called "IMSI-Catchers". These devices are used for man-in-the-middle attacks against mobile devices. They pretend to be legitimate cell towers, capturing and tracking traffic and device information. Law enforcement uses this data to take roll at protests, for example, and the NSA uses it to track targets to be taken out. Criminals use this to steal credit card numbers and passwords. The government's use of this technology is much scarier. All my traffic is run encrypted through Tor, so credit card information and passwords cannot be stolen locally. But tracking by the government for their evil purposes is still a possibility. I doubt the government would bomb me, honestly. I'm not a threat to national security and they don't need any more bad PR. But head counts are a realistic invasion of privacy. I suggest everyone use a prepaid anonymous SIM card if they have a mobile device, and install Android IMSI-Catcher Detector.

We got a spammer in #tor, repeatedly asking WHAT IS THE FUTURE OF TOR? WHATS PLANNED FOR 2016? in full capitals and pinging everyone. One thing led to another, and arma said a way we could all help prevent this sort of spam was by answering Tor-related questions online. I took a look at the linked site, and saw a very interesting one: Why does Claws Mail included in Tails generate PGP keys with only 1024 key length?. Claws Mail can use PGP!? The whole reason I use Icedove is because I never found a way to get Claws Mail to use PGP. I tracked down and installed the appropriate plugin, as well as Claws Mail, then purged Icedove. The Claws Mail PGP plugin has the same anti-feature that Enigmail does, the one that prevents pasting of passwords. It turns out pinentry is not Enigmail-specific, and is also used by the GnuPG plugin for Claws Mail.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

A lazy day

Day 00005: Thursday, 2015 March 12

I wanted to get at least one of three things done today:

get back into my online credit union account and online credit union credit card account, as well as report the credit card as compromised (due to not being able to log into any accounts to shut off autopay)
get my website set up as more than just a single XHTML page
start working on (but not likely finish today) getting a Minetest server up

Instead, I got none of these things done. I procrastinated until a surprise evening outing with my family came up and took up the rest of the night. It wasn't a bad outing, but I really should have gotten something done during the day when I had a chance.

Before this, I did walk down to the credit union to get the account situation sorted out. The people there were not able to fully restore access to both accounts, but they did reset my password on one account (I'm not even sure which), and said that if I logged in I could do the rest as well as regain access to the other account. I suspect that the account they reset the password on was the main credit union account. They said that they could not report the card as compromised, and that I would need to do that myself via telephone. Tomorrow, I should use the information they gave me to get in and fix things up. I hope I can report the card as compromised from the Web interface, because I really hate doing anything by telephone. Once I change carriers (and thus change telephone numbers), I will not be giving the new number out to hardly anyone, aside from potential and current employers. Service providers that I deal with, such as the credit union, will not be getting my number.

Android IMSI-Catcher Detector quit working on me today. Every time I opened the application, it crashed. Even clearing the application's data did not fix the crashing. After much testing, which involved me reverting several settings changes on the device and installing literately every non-system application I had (including Android IMSI-Catcher Detector itself), I finally found both how to get it back working and reproduce the issue so I could report it. It seems that when the device is restarted without first clearing the application's data, Android IMSI-Catcher Detector stops working until a time that the device is rebooted again with the cleared. I registered for GitHub so I could report the issue there, where the bug tracker is located, but my account was flagged as a bot account so I was unable to do anything. GitHub seems to have a habit of flagging the accounts of Tor users as robot accounts, but the thing is, they will work with you on that. If you tell them what is going on, they will restore usability to your account. I have contacted GitHub support, and now I just await a response.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

My money is back in my hands

Day 00006: Friday, 2015 March 13

CameraChimera of the Volatile Club showed me a fun toy today called TOIlet, a command line application that returns Unicode art output of the text for any ASCII text string entered. CameraChimera also showed me how to add this as a command to my IRC client so I can send formatted text to a channel on the fly.

It appears Gitorious has been bought out by the less freedom-friendly Gitlab. Gitorious' code is licensed under the terms of the GNU AGPL, while Gitlab instead has two branches, one under the MIT license and one under a proprietary license. The company uses the MIT-licensed branch to gather contributions from the community, then takes the good code and adds it to the proprietary branch. The proprietary branch includes features not in the MIT-licensed branch to get people to switch over to it and get locked into using it. I find this very sad. I was going to host my code on Gitorious, but as they are now disappearing in May, that isn't going to happen.

I got back into my main credit union account today using the information I got from walking into the credit union in person yesterday. However, this same information was not able to get me into the credit union credit card account as they had said it would. I decided to attempt a password recovery on the account, however, as expected, that required access to my old email address that I lost when my hard drive gave out. Recovering access to the email account seems to require first recovering access to the domain, but recovering access to the domain requires first recovering access to the email account. Unlike Gandi, the registrar this name is registered with does not provide a way to recover an account if you are unable to access your email.

I walked back down to the credit union, and this time ended up being helped by a different teller. He said he was aware that getting back into the main account wouldn't get me back into the secondary account, as they are, as I suspected, on different systems. He seemed confused that the other teller had thought one account was resetable from the other, which made me feel better, as I had been confused about how it could be done yesterday. He changed the email address associated with the account, after which I was able to perform the password reset from home. Best of all, it seems reporting the card as compromised is in fact possible from the Web interface.

The pattern that I thought I saw in Android IMSI-Catcher Detector's crashing was inaccurate. Not only do I not have a consistent way to avoid the error, I also don't have a consistent way to set it off. I still have not heard back from GitHub though, so I am still not able to report the bug to the developers.

As a final act for the day, I finished setting up my website in a usable way. All that exists here is still just my weblog, but the days are now separated into pages. There was an error in my numbering, it seems, and I had listed two days as day 4. That has been corrected as well. I should get my source code out there, bot so I don't lose it again, and so maybe someone can get a little use out of it.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Charls Davis and a potentially-compromised server

Day 00007: Saturday, 2015 March 14

I set up the <abbr/> and <acronym/> tags finally. I should have done it yesterday, but doing so required looking up the exact expansion of every abbreviation I've used on the site so far, and I was tired.

Someone named "Charls [sic] Davis" has decided to use an email address at my domain with his Apple account. I have never heard of Charls Davis, but I got a letter in my inbox asking me to confirm that the email address is really his. I attempted to contact Apple support through their website, but it seems that Tor users are banned from accessing Apple support via the Web. I also tried writing to Apple, but according to Apple's auto-responder, Apple doesn't read their email. The auto-responder instead directed me to the broken Web support page. Likewise, I have no way to find or contact Charls Davis and ask what's going on. I will likely waste much time tomorrow trying to reach Apple support, but tonight, I need to go to bed.

My server went down for unknown reasons. Normally, when that server malfunctions, it turns its fans up real loud and stops responding. Power-cycling the machine fixes the issue. However, this time, the machine was completely turned off. I don't know what would have caused it. On #Volatile, janicez thinks I got hacked. This may very well be the case. Watson said he had advice for me to help secure the server, find if anything was taken, and/or find if anything was left behind, but a net split immediately broke ended our conversation. I connected to the server he was using, but it then went down. The network server soon came back up, but watson was nowhere to be found.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

My canary chirps

Day 00009: Monday, 2015 March 16

I hoped to get some actual work done today, but again, I did not. I did not even get my new script to compile this website built. It's worth noting that I had a headache though, so I really wasn't up to doing much. I did however learn some very good information today.

First, I learned a new CSS trick from wowaname. The :active pseudo-class can be used to create dynamic menus that show sub-menus when a menu item is clicked. This trick does not require JavaScript at all, and even better, degrades quite gracefully. The most annoying part about JavaScript menus is that for users that do not or cannot have JavaScript enabled, the menus become unusable. The CSS solution is much more elegant though. Because the CSS contains only formating information and not any of the usable data, nothing important is lost when CSS is missing. CSS hides the sub-menus that are not in use, so when a user has CSS disabled or is using a Web browser that does not support CSS, all the menu items are simply displayed at once so they can all be reached.

It seems there is something known as the "onion cloner", and it copies the contents websites hosted at onion addresses. It replaces the Bitcoin addresses on any of the pages it copies with its own Bitcoin address, then makes the copies available at new onion addresses where they masquerade as the originals. I'm all for the spread of information. I believe anyone should be allowed to copy and redistribute anything and everything. However, masquerading as someone else is wrong and this could be some sort of man-in-the-middle attack. There is a relevant wiki article on this onion cloner, but the wiki is hosted at seems to be down.

The final thing I learned today, and perhaps the most important, is a trick known as a warrant canary. This little trick is a way around gag orders and other legal abominations that the government can serve you to steal your freedom to disclose what they do to you. It's subtle and it does not allow you to disclose the details of what you are doing. But with foresight, it allows you to disclose the fact that you are subjected to one of these orders at all. Basically, the key is to continually assert the fact that you are *not* under orders not to speak freely. As long as you continue to update this assertion, people know you have not been silenced. However, the moment your assertion has gone too long without being updated or especially if your assertion has been removed entirely, people who are watching know you *must* no longer be able to speak freely. Because you are not technically disclosing that you are under orders not to disclose something, it is completely legal. Until such an order is served to you, you are well within your rights to tell people that you have not been served a gag order. Starting today, if any of my weblog entries do not assert that I am still able to speak freely, *please assume I am not able to disclose something of great importance*. Likewise, if any entry in this weblog once held such a statement but no longer does, *please assume I am under orders from the government to remove such statements from past entries*, most likely to make it less obvious that the statements are not showing up in future entries.

I should create a list of known canaries at some point to help make it more obvious if one of them goes silent. As I got the idea from wowaname, I know that wowaname has a canary to start my list with.

Today, my canary chirped. If any future weblog entry does not mention my canary, I have been placed under orders by the government not to disclose something. If this notice is removed from this entry, the government has ordered me to retroactively censor myself. If you actively care about my wellbeing, please keep an eye on my canary.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

A mistake made and a plan to sign Web pages

Day 00010: Tuesday, 2015 March 17

It seems it was Jenny, not misted__, that showed me the PHP functions on Sunday. I have apologized, as well as added acknowledgement of the mistake to the correct weblog entry.

I got distracted yesterday by research on canaries and forgot to mention that my y.st. hostmask was approved on Volatile, so when I am logged in, I look like I'm coming from my domain despite the fact that I'm actually coming from the Tor network.

I decided to maybe add an automatic canary updater to my website's update script, though I don't know how that will be compatible with the decision to translate the update script to PHP. Once I find the time to set this up, I'll know more. To insure that failing to update the canary is entirely passive (as to avoid breaking the law), I'll add a --canary or --chirp command line flag, and if not included when running the script, it simply won't update the canary. In order for the canary to not disappear from the site when not updated, it will likely need to have a separate compile directory that compiles it into the static files directory before doing anything else. Because automating the canary update process will require finding a way to PGP sign from within PHP, I might as well sign all my pages at that time. It seems that there is no way to include the -----BEGIN PGP SIGNED MESSAGE-----, -----BEGIN PGP SIGNATURE-----, or -----END PGP SIGNATURE----- lines in XHTML comments and still have the page validate. This means that parts of the page will have to be outside the signed part of the page, which is unfortunate. I will likely sign only the content of <body/>.

According to the Canary Watch frequently-asked questions page, the government allows an entity to disclose approved ranges of gag orders they have been served over six-month periods. These ranges are all ranges of one thousand and start at zero, for example, 0 - 999. You can guarantee that if I start posting a range of the number of gag orders I have received, that I have received at least one. This is because as long as I am not bound by one of these gag orders, I am free to ignore the ranges and admit that I have received exactly zero of them. The power to issue these gag orders has been abused by the government for a while now, and the EFF is trying to raise awareness of it.

It seems the EFF is concerned about the privacy implications of whois records in DNS. I'm in total agreement, domain names should be allowed to be registered anonymously without need of a proxy (such as a whois privacy service).

It has been brought to my attention that Iceweasel blocks Web browsing on port 22 as well as other ports. I forget who showed me this, as I didn't write this entry until a couple days after I should have. I think it was mistedwind, but that's not important. I'm not sure what the goal in doing this way, but supposedly, it's somehow for security.

My last comment of the day is that I need to remember to stand up for everyone's rights, not just my own. I made a comment online about how I would be fine only being able to receive calls over SIP at my home server, as I never make any calls myself. Mistedwind reminded me that some people want to place calls from servers at their home addresses, and they have just as much right to place calls from home servers as I do to receive them from a home server. This was selfish of me, and I need to be more mindful of others in the future.

My canary sings freely today, signafying that I am still not under a gag order.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The discovery of minetest.register_biome()

Day 00015: Sunday, 2015 March 22

Early this morning, I set out to verify that PayPal is still giving me trouble and refusing to allow me to use their service. The plan was to hassle Bandcamp about it to try to get them to accept another form of payment. However, for some odd reason, PayPal accepted the payment from me. However tonight, PayPal has stopped accepting payments from me again, so I cannot buy the second album I was planning on buying. I think I will hassle PayPal (instead of Bandcamp) about it. I tried to reach PayPal support through their website, but as was the case last time I had issues with PayPal, they hide their contact information in an attempt to make those who would complain go away. As before, I've had to take this publicly to Twitter as I can't find another way to reach PayPal support.

In any case, I'm now the proud owner of a copy of Marc with a C's album An Introduction To Marc With a C. I bought the album to listen to "Love My Little Squiddy", but almost every song on the album is awesome. "Drunk Classic Rock Fans" is probably my favorite on the album. I hope to get the PayPal situation sorted out in a timely manor though, so I can get "I Will Repossess Your Heart" and the rest of Losing Salt.

I took a look at the output of PHP's highlight_string() function to see what I could do with it. I didn't get far. Things looked promising at first, but then I noticed that neither type of quotation mark was being encoded for use on a Web page. I thought it would cause substring replacement issues, but now as I type this, I think I realize I was wrong. I will again try to tackle the issue tomorrow.

After hitting a dead end with highlight_string(), I shut down Eschalot, which had been running on my server, and started up the Minetest server software. The current world served is just a test world, and the plan was that it would become corrupted as I slowly twisted minetest_game into minetyst_game. Once minetyst_game became presentable, I would delete the served world entirely and start anew with a more permanent world. I even added warnings of such in the server description and message of the day. However, once I started looking through the minetest_game code to start cleaning it up, I quickly chanced upon a function not listed in the Minetest API documentation: minetest.register_biome(). It seems this function defines the biomes for use in the v7 map generator, as well as probably in the v5 map generator. Only one biome is defined in minetest_game, but through experimenting, I found I can definitely get a second biome defined. The problem, however, is that I have no clue what I'm doing as I have no documentation to work with. minetest.register_biome() takes a single argument, a table containing entries labeled with particular keys. Most of the functionality of these keys can be figured out by just playing with the function and generating worlds, but y_min, y_max, heat_point, and humidity_point still confuse me. I would think that y_min and y_max would define the hight of the biome, but this isn't the case. Despite y_min being set to -32000, the biomes only extend down to -32, at which point mapgen_stone takes over. heat_point and humidity_point are no doubt used to decide which biomes are placed where, but they are single integers, not ranges, and I have no idea what happens when the heat and humidity noise conflict on what biome should go where. For example, I set a desert biome to have higher heat and lower humidity than the default biome. So what happens if an area has higher heat and higher humidity? Or lower heat and lower humidity? Which biome is placed there in these cases? In any case, if I can figure out how this function works, I should be able to set the map up to be exactly as I want it. All the other tricky biome stuff is easily accomplished using minetest.register_decoration().

PayPal is giving me grief, but the NSA and FBI currently aren't. My canary still sings and I may still speak freely today.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

PayPal is such a pain to work with

Day 00016: Monday, 2015 March 23

The people manning the PayPal Twitter account showed me how to contact PayPal through their website. The stupid part is, even once you navigate the small maze to reach the contact form, you are required to choose a topic with which you need support and there is no "other" option listed. If I chose the option relating to credit card support, the only available subtopics to choose from involve adding a card to tour account. As I don't have an account and am not trying to add a card to an account, merely pay with a card, I could not even choose the most relevant topic because choosing a subtopic is mandatory. I ended up having to file it as a general complaint. When choosing to file it as a complaint, the Web form recommends that you first contact support to try to get things sorted out. However, the complaint form was the only way I could find to reach support, aside from choosing an irrelevant topic to ask for support with. This form says PayPal will get back to me within 48 hours, but we'll see. I haven't had good luck with companies contacting me back lately. Speaking of which, GitHub still has not gotten back to me.

While I was picking up food at the store today, I dropped by the gift card section in hopes of picking up a reloadable PayPal gift card. The hope was that maybe with the gift card, PayPal would allow me to make payments, as PayPal is rejecting my credit card, despite having taken that same credit card recently. However, my local market didn't have PayPal gift cards. Perhaps I'll try another store later.

Not many are listening to me, but that doesn't mean my free speech has been stifled. My canary still sings the tune of freedom.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Minetyst will use mapgen v5

Day 00017: Tuesday, 2015 March 24

I've decided to develop minetyst_game mainly for use with the v5 map generator. It's not that I like the look of maps generated by this generator best, but that I think it has the most to offer in terms of game play. Four map generators are currently included in Minetest. The singlenode generator intentionally spits out nothing but a map containing a single type of node. The point is then that subgame designers that want to build the world entirely using the Lua API don't have to fight the C++ map generator, wasting resources having the map generator build its complex landscape only to have to undo what it has done. The singlenode generator represents endless potential, but that's it: only potential, nothing realized. It's awesome to have this option, but it's not what I'm going for. The v6 generator is the opposite. It is a very inflexible generator that builds the world in a very specific way. As a server administrator, you can adjust the sizes of things such as deserts and beaches. But as a subgame designer, adding your own types of areas such as biomes is very difficult and requires allowing the map generator to generate landscapes that you are going to overwrite yourself. That leaves us with the v5 and v7 generators. Don't let the names fool you; v5 was named after the algorithm used before v6, which v5 now partially employs, but the v5 generator is actually newer than the v7 generator and takes on some of its best qualities that did not exist prior to v7. The v5 and v7 map generators both create blank slate world by default, though not the same sort of blank slate world the singlenode generator creates. Rather, v5 and v7 generate the shape of the terrain, but nothing you would expect to see on the surface. There is no dirt, there are no trees. No beaches or deserts layered in sand. Everything you see on the surface is made of stone or water. Well, mostly. v5 additionally adds small patches of dirt and gravel. However, we don't have only the default blank slate worlds to work with. The v5 and v7 map generators also give us the undocumented minetest.register_biome() function I found two days ago. With this, we can easily define biomes that the map generator will generate on the surface with a depth down through y=-31. At y=-32 and below, the map generator seems to ignore biomes and do whatever it feels like. This is fine, but must be taken into account when choosing which generator to use. The v7 generator seems to offer more interesting shapes both above and below the surface, but the v5 generator offers more types of nodes below the surface.

When I say I'm mainly going to focus on the v5 map generator in minetyst_game, I don't mean that I won't do what it takes to support the other map generators. I will define all the map generator aliases to make sure each map generator reaches its full potential. In fact, I'll use the existing aliases in other map generators as a template for setting up my initial biomes in v5 and v7. However, if the node shows up in v5, I may not makes sure it shows up elsewhere. For example, gravel spawns naturally in v5 and in v6, but it may not be made available in v7. The "default:*" nodes will be added using a biome, so they may not be made available in v6. This isn't unlike minetest_game though, which makes most nodes unavailable to any map that isn't using the v6 generator.

My speech is still free. I am not under a gag order.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Debugging Minetyst

Day 00018: Wednesday, 2015 March 25

I spent a lot of time yesterday and today experimenting with the minetest.register_biome() function. For the time being, I'm assuming the temperature and humidity ranges to be 0 - 100, though evidence points to this not being the case. I've asked about it in the Minetest forum in hopes that someone, *anyone*, knows what they're doing with this undocumented function. The minetest comunity in general, and in particular certain active members, is known for being very helpful to people trying to learn the ins and outs of the game. If someone knows something about this function, it is very likely I will get a response.

Some of my first experimentation went oddly due to a mistake in my code. Mossy cobble was showing up scattered in all the stone in my world! It turns out I had accidentally aliased both mapgen_stone and mapgen_cobble to the basic:stone node. It seems that the dungeons are built out of cobble first, then all cobble on the map is given a chance to possibly be swapped out for mossy cobble. As I already know from a previous world where I intentionally mapped *all* the map generator alias aliases to the same node, having multiple map generator aliases mapped to the same node causes odd results. Last time, I ended up with trees growing out of trees endlessly upward. My guess is that because the leaves at the tops of the trees were the same node as the ground, they were interpreted as the ground and it was assumed that the jungle there had not actually generated yet. The map generator algorithm called for a jungle at those coordinates, so it built the jungle repeatedly at this ever-upward-rising land.

Once I got the mossy cobble issue debugged, I moved on to actually defining some biomes. My six biomes for the time being are based on the nodes in the default module, both in minetest_game and in minimal. From the nodes in minetest_game's default, I have set up the grassland, forest, jungle, alpine, and desert biomes. Most of these are based on nodes asked for by the v6 map generator, but the alpine biome is thrown in as a way to acquire the pine trees from default. It doesn't make a bad place for placing snow, either. The final biome is the retro biome, a biome dedicated to nodes in minetyst_game's default module. Minetyst_game's default represents the legacy code in the Minetest engine. Code that translates old maps to work with the current engine, but does so in a hacky way. Specifically, it causes the engine to ask for nodes in the default module, instead of using aliases as it should. This makes it a pain to set your game up to handle legacy maps unless you either employ a default module that holds everything the engine needs for legacy maps or you avoid setting up a default module and instead use the names from default as aliases. The proper way to do this would be to rely on the mapgen_* aliases for this job, or perhaps set up new legacy_* aliases. In any case, minetyst_game's default holds all the "default:*" nodes the engine asks for and no other nodes.

My initial biome layout yesterday wasn't working out well. I had four biomes set in the assumed corner cases, one dead center in the heat/humidity layout, and one slightly off from dead center. I tried a few different similar layouts, but every time, there was at least one biome that was so rare that it took forever to find an example of it. Eventually, I decided on a more even layout, where heat for each biome was set to 100/6, 50, or 500/6 and humidity was set to either 100/6 or 500/6. If the biome generation works as I think it does, which is via a least squares function involving the heat and humidity, this should make every biome appear equally as often (assuming that the heat and humidity ranges are both 0 - 100, which I do not believe to actually be the case). As predicted, this makes every biome show up fairly often, though some seem to be more likely to appear than others.

I still am able to speak freely.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

paramat to the rescue

Day 00019: Thursday, 2015 March 26

Paramat showed up to help me in the Minetest forum. It's been a while since I was last a part of the Minetest community, but last I knew, paramat was the king of perlin noise and map generation. Having paramat to assist me was even better than I could have hoped for. It seems that I wasn't far off in my assumption that heat and humidity ranges are from 0 to 100. The actual range is from -25 to 125, but values outside the range of 0 to 100 are rare. I will probably try to crunch the numbers tomorrow to find rarity of these ranges so I can more evenly distribute my biomes. Paramat also showed me the biomesdev module he/she built, so I can use it as an example of how to use the biome-generating functions.

At work today, my mobile was having issues. Orbot wouldn't stop crashing as soon as it was no longer the application in focus. When I would open the application drawer, it would crash almost every time as well. The timer application, which I use to time my breaks, wouldn't make any sound while the screen was off, causing me to break for too long. I didn't have time to debug right away, but after I clocked off, I tried rebooting the device. Everything was then in working order. Or so it seemed. I later took a trip to the thrift store, where I ended up needing to access the Internet. This is the first time I've gone clothing shopping since I became vegan, and I wasn't sure what some of the materials the clothing was made of were. I pulled out my mobile to look up the materials by the names listed on the tags, and found that my mobile had forgotten the network access point. While I had full tower connectivity, I did not have the information needed to actually access the network. I would only be able to look up the information needed to feed into the mobile and get the Internet connection back up once I got home. I took a risk and bought a linen shirt not knowing for sure what linen is, but but passed on everything else that I didn't know what it was. I forgot to fix the mobile's data connection when I got home, but later started receiving alerts that email was coming in. At first, I thought nothing of it, but then I realized that I shouldn't be getting email because I wasn't connected to the Internet. I checked in the mobile's settings, and sure enough, it had remembered the access point information. I am completely baffled as to what is going on with the device right now.

As a note, I later looked up what linen is. It is a fabric made from the fibers of the flax plant, and is therefor vegan-friendly.

I contacted GitHub for the third time through their Web form. If they do not respond this time, I will try contacting them through Twitter.

My mother is really into Geocaching. One of her friends has scheduled a Geocaching event and is trying to get at least five hundred people to log that they will attend, as this will cause the event to be reclassified by the website as a "mega event". Apparently it will be the first in this state. I registered an account to help with this, however, it seems the site prohibits access to the page by proxies. I am behind Tor as always, so I am unable to access the event page to log that I will attend. Oddly enough, the Geocaching website *did* allow me to register an account from behind Tor, it just won't allow me to see the description and logging pages.

I am not under orders not to speak freely.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

PayPal and their semingly-automated responses

Day 00021: Saturday, 2015 March 28

I received a response from PayPal, and it shows just how incompetent they are. I had to submit my request in the form of a formal complaint because of a combination of factors relating to their idiotic system. Because I don't hava an account, I have to choose a category of inquiry, and none of the available categories fit the issue. I explained all of this in my complaint, yet in their response, they said next time I should use the contact form that I explained why I couldn't use.

Next, PayPal said that because the email address I gave them is not associated with an account, they were unable to locate my failed transaction. There are two issues with this. First of all, I told them that the transaction was not made with an account. Or rather, I told them that I had no account, which if they had any intelegence, would tell them that any transaction I make throughh them is not accosiated with an account. Yet they still tried to locate my account by my email address. Second, I've had this same issue before in the past, even back when I had an account. When PayPal declines your card, they *fail to log that a transaction attempt was even made*. Not finding the transaction has nothing to do with not finding the account. Because the card was declined by PayPal, PayPal doesn't even keep record of it.

Next, PayPal tells me that if I have further questions, I need to contact telephone support. I thought I had told them that I do not have a telephone, but looking back over my initial message to them, I did not. I suppose I will let this one slide because of that. However, redirecting people to telephone support is not a valid way to handle issues. Telephone support is agrovating and time consuming. Not to mention the fact that not everyone has a telephone and it should not be expected that everyone does.

I tweeted almost verbatim most of the above (publicly) to @AskPayPal. We'll see if that gets me anywhere. I have also recontacted PayPal through the form they asked me too. I chose the category "How do I spend money" under "Sending/Reciving money", which isn't quite the right category, but it seems to be the closest they offer.

Waking up several times in the middle of the night, I manages to install the system with an encrypted /home directory before having to go to work in the morning. I'm not too happy with the results though. I have to enter my password three times before the system fully comes up (once for the encrypted swap partition that the installer insisted on and is probably a good idea, and twice for the encrypted /home partition). That's fine, but it seems that if I make a typographical error when entering the password, the system throws a fit, fails to boot properly, then dumps me in a root console. The proper way to handle it would be to request the password again, but instead, it hands root access over to whoever doesn't have the password. That seems like a security issue wating to happen. Sure, they can't access my sensitive data right away, but with root access, they can install whatever they like on my machine. They could for example install a key logger or a way to remotely access my data next time I mount the file system. I'm going to try something new when I get off work.

For the time being, I am still not under a gag order.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Technical difficulties: please stand by

Day 00022: Sunday, 2015 March 29

Due to technical difficulty today, I missed the deadline of my canary. Honestly, I'm alright. I can still speak freely legally, I just have a tendency to have complications when trying something new. This just goes to show that if I'm doing something new to my computer, I really should first update my site to give myself the most time possible in getting back to the canary.

First of all, PayPal has agreed to take a look at my successful transaction if I send them an email originating from the email address I made the purchase from. They haven't yet agreed to do anything about the failed purchases, but it's a start. This happened yesterday, but I was unable to act on it yesterday or today. As you may know, I use a catch-all email address and give a different email address to every site that requests my email address. This allows me to know who gave out and/or sold my email address to spammers if I start getting a bunch of spam. The email address is usually in the form of "{their host name including the terminating dot}@{my domain excluding the terminating dot}", though some sites claim this address is invalid. In these cases, I leave off the terminating dot from their domain name, and the site then accepts the address. Due to the nature of catch-all addresses, these addresses are perfectly valid and mail sent to them reaches me. However, they are inbound addresses only, not outbound. Assuming Zoho (my mail host) allows user names ending in dots, I should be able to set up the address I gave PayPal as an outbound address and continue with my attempts to get them to allow my to buy Mark With a C's music.

Yesterday, after writing up my weblog entry for the day, I began my attempts to encrypt my hard drive. I tried to avoid doing it the right way, as the right way involves either modifying the Libreboot firmware (which I am not comfortable doing as I might brick my laptop) or entering five GRUB commands every time you want to boot the machine. However, it seems that the right way is the only way. The Debian installer won't let you do it the wrong way. If you set up the encrypted partition not knowing about /boot, you will reach a state in the installer where the installer demands that you set up a /boot partition, but the installer also refuses to allow you to shrink an existing partition to make room for the /boot partition. You can't move forward and you can't move back. You have to restart the machine and try again. The most time consuming part of the installation is that whenever anything goes wrong and you have to begin the install again, the installer wants to overwrite the whole disk with random data (only when using encryption). That means that each mistake and failed installation cost me a lot of time, which is why I missed my canary deadline. At one point, the installer set the system up fully-encrypted (using the right method mentioned above), but somehow failed to install sudo. I couldn't install sudo myself because I needed sudo to have the privileges needed to install anything. I tried using Synaptic to install it, but Synaptic asked for root's password. I didn't set a root password for security reasons, so I was unable to make installations that way either. Once again, I had to go through the time-consuming process of reinstalling the encrypted system.

Tomorrow (which is the day I actually wrote this entry), I would finally succeed in the installation.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

They will ship glitter to your enemies

Day 00024: Tuesday, 2015 March 31

Bandcamp wrote back to me stating that PayPal is currently the only method of payment that they accept (which I already knew and was the reason for my letter to them), but that they are currently exploring more flexible options. Whether this exploration was prompted by me or not was left unstated, but I get the feeling that I did not instigate this. Bandcamp has likely received complaints about PayPal issues from other users as well and was already in the process of trying to allow other payment processing options before I wrote. I was worried that Bandcamp would not be open to my suggestion, but it seems things are already in the works.

Speaking of PayPal, clearing things up without a PayPal account was much easier than back when I had an account. As I said yesterday, my payment through PayPal suddenly was able to go through. I don't know if PayPal fixed the issue because of my complaining and simply did not tell me (doubtful) or if the issue simply went away for the time being. When I had an account, PayPal support kept demanding sensitive information from me (most of which I was gullible enough to hand over at the time),after which they would claim they had unlocked my account. However, the next time I tried to log in, I would find my account either still locked or locked again. This carried on for almost two months. However, this time, things cleared up in a little over a week. I have no doubt that this issue will occur again repeatedly, but it seems it doesn't last so long as long as I don't have an account.

Mistedwind told me about the existence of a onion and eepsite certificate authority, and said the link was on along list of links somewhere. Finding it was easy with the browser's search option, but I also looked through the list and found several other interesting things. The certificate authority seems to not be issuing certificates for the time being, but the process they use to verify that you own a given onion or eepsite is your own by submitting a PGP-signed request using a key claiming to be valid for a specific email address at your domain. I don't see how this proves anything, as anyone can generate such a key, and I think even multiple people can upload such a key to the same key server. However, it is an interesting concept. There is also a site that sells the service of shipping your enemies glitter.

I don't know how, but someone has found my onion address. I don't try to hide it, but I'm not particularly noteworthy and my onion mostly just sits there offering a copy of the Eschalot source code. Somehow though, it has made its way onto a list of onions.

Paramat got back to me on my question about the temperature and humidity ranges right away, but due to my recent technical problems, I was unable to reply until yesterday. But I was very tired yesterday and put off reading paramat's response until today. It seems my hunch about the range was right. But while the values can get as low as -37.5 and as high as +137.5, they rarely do. I will probably move the generic biome back to the center of the temperature/humidity map, move the four other major biomes to near the corners of the 0 to 100 range, and split the retro biome into four more specific biomes containing different old nodes. These four new biomes will exist at the extremes of the temperature/humidity map and will be the rarest biomes of all.

I am considering joining Josh Woodward's funding efforts, but not tonight. Patreon's terms of service are simply too long, and I don't feel up to reading them tonight. In addition to reading those terms, I should pester GitHub on Twitter tomorrow. They still have not responded to me about activating my account. If they don't want to activate my account, that's one thing, but they should at least respond to me telling me that they will not. I can inly assume that their contact form is broken or something and they are not even getting my cries for help.

My right to free speech is still intact.

Copyright © 2015 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.